<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | @_ddrscott_]]></title>
  <link href="http://ddrscott.github.io/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ddrscott.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-13T14:40:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ddrscott.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Pierce]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ddrscott@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress to the Rescue]]></title>
    <link href="http://ddrscott.github.io/blog/2014/octopress-to-the-rescue/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-16T23:31:31-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ddrscott.github.io/blog/2014/octopress-to-the-rescue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="featured" src="/images/octopress_logo.png" width="227" height="227" title="&lsquo;Octopress Logo&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>After nearly a year without Posterous, I&rsquo;ve finally got around to migrating to another system.
This time around it&rsquo;s a static blog builder: <a href="http://octopress.org/">http://octopress.org/</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Octopress is a wrapper around Jekyll which is a utility for creating a static blogging site. A blog that can be
hosted on anything that can server files: Apache, AWS, Dropbox, etc&hellip;</p>

<h3>Q: Why not use WordPress, Tumbler, Blogger?!?</h3>

<p>Those tailor to non-developers and their editors are not the ones I use everyday, my IDE. Octopress lets me
write my articles the same way as I write code: plain text. It uses markdown or any other HTML generator I configure.</p>

<p>Static pages are easier for me to deploy when I have to switch hosting providers. Hopefully Github sticks around
for a while, but if they don&rsquo;t, I can rest assured I can have the article hosted some where else faster than DNS propagation.</p>

<p>``` ruby
puts &ldquo;I can use code snippets&rdquo;</p>

<h1>And they will be nicely formatted.</h1>

<p>maybe_one_day do
  use(CodePen) or use(jsFiddle)
end
```</p>

<p>The initial theme I selected is <a href="https://github.com/sevenadrian/MediumFox.">https://github.com/sevenadrian/MediumFox.</a> It&rsquo;s clean, simple and pretty much
what I would have <em>tried</em> to make if I had time. They seemed to have omitted some features from the classic theme, but
as with all Open Source projects it is easy to remedy.</p>

<p>Time to post to do my first deploy&hellip; then convert all the Posterous archives.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>